INVENTORY TO THE PIERCE FAMILY PAPERS, 1841-1940 D-022
University of California, Davis General Library, Dept. of Special Collections
- George W. Pierce, Jr., 1864-1931; Series 3.; 1328 Linear Feet
  - Correspondence, n.d., 1876-1931; Subseries 3.1.; 398 items
    - Incoming, 1876-1931; Subseries 3.1.2.; 322 items
      - Johnson, Hiram W., Governor of California; Alexander McCabe, Private Secretary [for Gov. Johnson];; letter, Feb. 18, 1913; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 11.2)
      - Lake Tahoe Railway and Transportation Company; J. U. Haley, General Freight and Passenger Agent;; letter, annual pass, and envelope, April 28, 1903; 3 items (Box 3, Folder 12.1)
      - Lang, Herbert, letter and envelope, June 13, 1905; 2 items (Box 3, Folder 12.2)
      - Marsh Brothers and Gardenier Inc., Contracting Engineers; Marsh, E. L., President;; letter, Dec. 17, 1914; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 12.3)
      - Montgomery, Carey, letter, March 30, 1913; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 12.4)
      - Myers, T. L., (regarding Silica Brick Company), letter with estimate, March 31, 1911; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 12.5)
      - New Orleans Board of Control, Department of Publicity, National Drainage Congress, 2 letters and 1 flier, 1912; 3 items (Box 3, Folder 13.1)
      - Newby, B. F., letter from Newby with 2 letters from Hugo K. Asher enclosed, 1918; 3 items (Box 3, Folder 13.2)
      - O'Connor, Annie, incomplete date, letter, 1 item (Box 3, Folder 13.3)
      - Official Committee for the Reception of the Fleet, invitation, ticket, and envelope, May 6, 1908; 3 items (Box 3, Folder 13.4)
      - Pacific Gas and Electric Company; S. V. Walton, Manager Commercial Department; (regarding Silica Brick Company);; letter, Nov. 23, 1910; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 14.1)
      - Pardee, George C., Governor of California; incomplete date,; 1 telegram, 4 letters, and 2 envelopes, 1905-1913; 7 items (Box 3, Folder 14.2)
      - [Pierce, Susan Gilmore], "Susie,", letter, Sept. 4, 1909; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 14.3)
      - Pierson, J. C., 5 letters and 1 envelope, 1882-1883; 6 items (Box 3, Folder 14.4)
      - Rose, Charles T., n.d., 2 letters, 1913; 2 items (Box 3, Folder 14.5)
      - Sacramento Clay Products Company; J. P. Dargitz, Secretary;, letter and envelope, Nov. 18, 1914; 2 items (Box 3, Folder 15.1)
      - Sacramento Union; Alfred Holman, Editor and Publisher;; letter, April 20, 1905; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 15.2)
      - Sacramento Valley Electric Railroad Company; Melville Dozier, Jr., General Manager; n.d.,; 1 letter from Dozier with the following enclosed: copy of letter sent to H. R. Timm, copy of letter sent to John Reith, Jr., copy of letter sent to stockholders by E. L. Sisson, and envelope with notes, 1914; 5 items (Box 3, Folder 15.3)
      - Sacramento Valley Electric Railroad Company; Louis L. Janes, Secretary;; 2 letters and 1 envelope, 1914; 3 items (Box 3, Folder 15.4)
      - Sacramento Valley Expositions Commission; William J. Weyand, Acting President;; letter, Oct. 19,1915; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 15.5)
      - Scarlett, J. E., 2 letters, 1918; 2 items (Box 3, Folder 15.6)
      - Silica Brick Company; J. P. Dargitz, Secretary;; 11 letters and 1 clipping, 1911-1912; 12 items (Box 3, Folder 16)
      - Singh, Mousha, letter, April 9, 1914; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 17.1)
      - Shore Line Investment Company; Charles W. Fay, General Manager;; letter, March 18, 1912; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 17.2)
      - Southern Pacific Company; J. D. Brennen, Superintendent Western Division;; letter, Feb. 17, 1913; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 17.3)
      - Southern Pacific Company; James Horsburgh, Jr., Asst. Gen. Pass. Agent;; 2 letters and 2 envelopes, 1903; 4 items (Box 3, Folder 17.4)
      - Stanley, Martha C., n.d., letter, 1 item (Box 3, Folder 17.5)
      - State Farm Commission; V. H. Henderson; Secretary;; 7 letters and 7 envelopes, 1905-1906; 14 items (Box 3, Folder 17.6)
      - Stevens, Flora J., letter, Oct. 3, 1907; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 17.7)
      - Throof, D. R., letter, March 11, 1913; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 18.1)
      - True, Gordon H., illegible date, letter and envelope, 2 items (Box 3, Folder 18.2)
      - Tufts, Addie B., n.d., letter, card, and envelope, 1927; 3 items (Box 3, Folder 18.3)
      - United States. Department of Agriculture, Bureau of Statistics, county schedule, Dec. 1, 1903; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 19.1)
      - University of California, Davis. College of Agriculture, Faculty Club; University Farm; n.d.,; letters from E. H. Hughes and J. D. Long, Manager; form letters from the Board of Directors and the Social Committee., 1925; 4 items (Box 3, Folder 19.2)
      - University of California, Davis. College of Agriculture, Horticulture Round Table; University Farm;; letter, Jan. 20, 1924; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 19.3)
      - University of California, Davis. College of Agriculture; University Farm Creamery;; form letter and envelope, Sept. 25, 1915; 2 items (Box 3, Folder 19.4)
      - University of California, Davis. College of Agriculture; University Farm; H. E. Van Norman, Dean;; letter, Oct. 2, 1915; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 19.5)
      - University of California. Revenue Association; William Denman, Secretary;; letter and envelope, Dec. 31, 1900; 2 items (Box 3, Folder 19.6)
      - University of California. Volunteer Committee, Class of 1875, n.d., form letter, 1 item (Box 3, Folder 19.7)
      - Webb, U. S., Attorney-General of California;; 2 letters, 2 envelopes, enclosed copy of a letter from Webb to Gov. George C. Pardee, and enclosed copy of a letter from Webb to V. H. Henderson, Aug. 1906; 6 items (Box 3, Folder 20.1)
      - Wheeler, Benjamin Ide, 2 letters and 2 envelopes, 1905-1906; 4 items (Box 3, Folder 20.2)
      - Wickson, E. J., 5 letters, 1 telegram, and 4 envelopes, 1905-1906; 10 items (Box 3, Folder 20.3)
      - Wilkins, C. W., letter and envelope, July 15, 1931; 2 items (Box 3, Folder 20.4)
      - Woodland Daily Democrat; Edward E. Leake, Editor and Proprietor; n.d.,; 3 letters and envelope, 1915; 4 items (Box 3, Folder 20.5)
      - Yolo County Board of Trade; H. S. Maddox, Secretary-Manager; n.d.,; 2 letters, envelope, flier, 1913; 4 items (Box 3, Folder 20.6)
      - Yolo County Consolidated Water Company; J. Craig, President;; 2 letters, Feb. 16, 1906; 2 items (Box 3, Folder 20.7)
      - Yolo County Consolidated Water Company; W. H. Gregory, Manager;; letter, July 16, 1906; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 20.8)
      - Unidentified Author; invitation to grand ball, Yolo County, CA, May 1, 1876; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 21.1)
      - Unidentified Author; empty envelope mailed from Sacramento, CA, Feb. 10, 1915; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 21.2)
      - Associated Almond Growers of Paso Robles; C. E. Magahy, Secretary; n.d.; form, letter, booklet, and envelope., 4 items (Box 12, Folder 1)
      - Sacramento Valley Electric Railroad Company; Louis L. Janes, Secretary;; large envelope, Dec. 8, 1914; 1 item (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Collected Letters, 1866-1920; Subseries 3.1.3.; 15 items
      These collected letters (1866-1920, 15 items) may have been enclosed in letters sent to George W. Pierce, Jr. They pertain to topics important to Pierce such as Silica Brick Company, the proposed University Farm site, Yolo County, CA promotion, and various agricultural products. Letters between Governor George C. Pardee and Senator U. S. Webb are included in the collected letters subseries.
      - California State Prison, Folsom, CA; Warden John McComb to Sperry and Company;; letter, May 13, 1887; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 22.1)
      - Guile, D. B. to M. Diggs, incomplete date, letter, 1 item (Box 3, Folder 22.2)
      - Hannon, W. to Sacramento Bank, letter, Aug. 9, 1892; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 22.3)
      - Hilgard, E. W. to W. A. Beard, copy of letter, March 22, 1911; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 22.4)
      - Lamont, George A. to R. B. Armstrong, letter and copy of that letter, June 5, 1906; 2 items (Box 3, Folder 22.5)
      - Lawrence, J. H. to Messrs. R. N. and C. D., letter, Dec. 31, 1866; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 22.6)
      - [Pardee, George C.], Governor of California, to U. S. Webb, cc. letter, May 8, 1906; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 22.7)
      - Sacramento Valley Home Products League; C. T. Farnham to Davis Chamber of Commerce, Davis, CA;; letter, Feb. 17, 1913; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 22.8)
      - Schlegel, Frank H. to M. Diggs, letter, Oct. 28, 1908; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 22.9)
      - Schmeiser Manufacturing Company, Davis, CA; ca.; form letter/brochure for the Read - Schmeiser Almond Huller and Separator No. 2. Letter features quote from Pierce's article "The Almond.", 1920; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 22.10)
      - Scott, G. W. to William [illegible last name], letter, March 14, 1888; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 22.11)
      - Southern Pacific Company; J. D. Brennan, Supt. Western Division; to H. S. Maddox, Secretary, Yolo County Board of Trade;; letter, Feb. 9, 1913; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 22.12)
      - Vinter, William of Hope Orchard, Edenville, CA to Holmes Lime Company, Inc.;; copy of letter, Dec. 23, 1908; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 22.13)
      - Webb, U. S., Attorney-General of California, (by E. B. Power, Deputy) to George C. Pardee, Governor of California;; copy of letter, May 26, 1906; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 22.14)
  - Legal Documents, 1870-1927, Subseries 3.2.; 62 items
    The Legal Documents subseries contains documents having to do with Farmers' Marketing Organizations, Property and Water Rights, Public Office, Silica Brick Company, and Other topics. Within these subject headings, items are organized by format. Farmers' marketing organizations covered in the Legal Documents subseries are the California Almond Growers' Exchange, the Davisville Almond Growers' Association (Davis Almond Growers' Association), the Farmers' Protective Association of California, the California Fruit Distributors, the California Grain Growers' Association, and the California Fruit Growers, Committee on Labor. Property and water rights records include many important legal documents for Pierce Family properties, records having to do with University of California history and the founding of the University Farm at Davis, CA, and documents pertaining to various Yolo County, CA properties and water companies. Public office records relate to just two of the several offices held by Pierce. Records for Silica Brick Company are also contained in the Legal Documents subseries. The Other category contains legal documents having to do with life insurance, the building of a national highway, and the Porfirio Diaz government of Mexico.
    - Farmers' Marketing Associations, 1901-1917, Subseries 3.2.1.; 12 items
      - Agreements and Contracts; California Almond Growers' Exchange, Davisville Almond Growers' Association (Davis Almond Growers' Association); n.d., 1903-1906; 6 items (Box 3, Folder 23)
      - By-laws of the Farmers' Protective Association of California, 1903; 3 items (Box 3, Folder 24.1)
      - Resolutions; California Fruit Distributors; California Grain Growers' Association; California Fruit Growers, Committee on Labor; n.d., 1901-1917, 3 items (Box 3, Folder 24.2)
    - Property and Water Rights, 1883-1927, Subseries 3.2.2.; 27 items
      The subseries, Property and Water Rights, includes many legal documents for Pierce Family properties, important records having to do with University of California history and the founding of the University Farm at Davis, CA, and documents relating to various Yolo County, CA properties and water companies.
      - Pierce Family Properties, 1904-1927, 9 items
        These legal documents having to do with properties owned by the Pierce Family include an agreement/contract for home renovations, property insurance policies, and a notice "to the users of water passing through the Pierce lateral irrigation canal."
        - Agreement/Contract; Charles T. Rose and George W. Pierce, Jr., Sept. 7, 1912; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 25.1)
        - Insurance Policies for Property; Norwich Union Fire Insurance Society, Hartford Fire Insurance Company, and German American Insurance Company;; 4 policies and 1 letter, 1904-1906; 5 items (Box 10, Folder 6)
        - Notice, Sept. 1927; 3 items (Box 3, Folder 25.2)
      - University Farm site: University of California, Davis, 1905-1906; 12 items
        12 items among the legal documents of George W. Pierce, Jr. have to do with property and water rights and the site for the University Farm. These items are very important to those researching the founding of the University of California, Davis. This subseries contains a formal offer of a site for the University Farm. The land known as the M. V. Sparks place was offered by a committee of citizens of Yolo County, CA to the State Farm Commission in 1905. Also, in this subseries are agreements and contracts between parties including the citizens of Davisville, CA, M. V. Sparks, George W. Pierce, Jr., the Yolo County Consolidated Water Company, and the Regents of the University of California. Because of their importance, these documents had been separated from this collection--the Pierce Family Papers--put into a portfolio, and cataloged as a book. Now they are reunited with the collection of papers from which they came so that researchers may see these documents in their proper context.
        - Agreements and Contracts, 1905-1906; 11 items
          Agreements and Contracts are part of the legal documents belonging to the George W. Pierce, Jr. Series. They are agreements and contracts related to the acquisition of property and water rights for the University of California's proposed University Farm in 1905-1906.
          - Citizens of Davisville, CA, regarding fund to pay for water rights for the University Farm and interest on purchase price of the M. V. Sparks place, 1906; 3 items (Box 3, Folder 26)
          - Sparks, M. V. and George W. Pierce, Jr., 6 agreements and envelope., 1905-1906; 7 items (Box 3, Folder 27)
            General note
            Regarding purchase of land for the University Farm and Yolo County Consolidated Water Company stock.
          - Yolo County Consolidated Water Company and the Regents of the University of California, July 23, 1906; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 28)
        - Formal Offer, copy., May 12, 1905; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 29)
          Committee of citizens of Yolo County, CA offer site known as the M. V. Sparks Place to the State Farm Commission.
      - Various Yolo County, CA properties and water companies, 1883-1913; 6 items
        These legal documents belonging to George W. Pierce, Jr. (Series III) and pertaining to property and water rights, do not particularly have to do with the Pierce Family properties nor the University Farm. These documents instead relate to various Yolo County, CA properties and water companies. An agreement, by-laws, and records of a court decision and a lawsuit make up this subseries.
        - Agreement; M. Diggs and G. Miner;., Jan. 22, 1908; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 30)
          Concerning rental of Hext Ranch subdivision lots.
        - By-laws of Putah Creek Water Company, 1883; 3 items (Box 3, Folder 31)
        - Court Decision; Moore vs. Capay Ditch Company;., 1902; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 32)
          In the Superior Court of the County of Yolo and the State of California
        - Lawsuit; Ernest V. Cowell Estate vs. multiple defendants for rights to the water of Putah Creek;., 1913; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Public Office, ca., 1898-1900; Subseries 3.2.3.; 4 items
      Legal documents pertaining to two of the many public offices held by George W. Pierce, Jr. are contained in the subseries, Public Office. A large certificate and its envelope have to do with the appointment of Pierce as a trustee of the California. State Normal School, San Jose. Two petitions containing the names of residents of Yolo County, CA, circa 1898, support the Republican Pierce's candidacy for the office he later held--representative in the California State Assembly of 1898 and 1899.
      - Appointment and Commission; Henry T. Gage, Governor of California, appoints George W. Pierce, Jr. as a trustee of the California. State Normal School, San Jose;., 1900; 2 items (Box 10, Folder 7)
      - Petitions; Residents of Yolo County, CA to George W. Pierce, Jr., ca., 1898; 2 items (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Silica Brick Company, 1911-1912; Subseries 3.2.4.; 3 items
      Items in the Silica Brick Company subseries are legal documents and part of Series III, George W. Pierce, Jr. Two propositions relating to the business of the Silica Brick Company and the Sacramento Clay Products Company as well as a writ of attachment against the brick company are included in this subseries.
      - Propositions, 1912; 2 items (Box 3, Folder 35.1)
      - Writ of Attachment; Clinton L. White vs. Silica Brick Company, Dec. 4, 1911; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 35.2)
    - Other Legal Documents, 1870-1913; Subseries 3.2.5.; 14 items
      The subseries, Other Legal Documents, is made up of various legal documents within Series III, George W. Pierce, Jr., that do not have to do with farmers' marketing organizations, property and water rights, public office, nor Silica Brick Company. Organized by format the documents in this subseries include a California State Assembly Bill, a club's constitution, materials related to life insurance, and two resolutions.
      - Assembly Bill No. 553, California State Assembly, "An act to provide for the survey and construction of wagon road from Tallac to McKinney's, along the shore of Lake Tahoe,", 1897; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 36.1)
      - Constitution of the Yolo County Club of the University of California, 1895; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 36.2)
      - Life Insurance Policies; Sonoma and Marin Mutual Beneficial Association and Standard Life and Accident Insurance Company; application, brochure, policy with supplement, envelope, and 2 letters., ca. 1870-1905; 7 items (Box 3, Folder 37)
      - Resolutions, n.d., ca., 1913; 5 items
        - Resolution by Davis Chamber of Commerce, Davis, CA, ca., concerning national highway., 1913; 3 items (Box 3, Folder 38.1)
        - Resolution of California State Assembly, Joint Resolution No. 44, recognition of Porfirio Diaz government of Mexico, n.d., 2 items (Box 3, Folder 38.2)
  - Financial Records, 1882-1925; Subseries 3.3.; 172 items
    The third subseries of Series III, George W. Pierce, Jr., is Financial Records. Pierce's financial records have been divided into 4 categories: Tax Records; Tax Records (Oversize); Account Statements, Promissory Notes, and Receipts; and Account Books. The tax records and oversize tax records (segregated by size for preservation reasons) consist of receipts for taxes paid to the cities of Davis, CA and Woodland, CA; the United States, Internal Revenue Service; and Yolo County, CA. Also included are receipts for taxes that Pierce paid for tracts of land deeded to the Regents of the University of California. Pierce's account statements, promissory notes, and receipts are not related to taxes but are records of other family and ranch business. 4 account books are part of the financial records subseries, but along with these books come numerous notes, clippings, and receipts.
    - Tax Records, 1904-1918; 6 items (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Tax Records (Oversize), 1899-1918; 3 items (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Account Statements, Promissory Notes, and Receipts, n.d., incomplete date, 1885-1925; 126 items
      - Statements, notes, receipts, n.d., incomplete date, 9 items (Box 3, Folder 40)
      - Statements, notes, receipts, 1885-1904; 23 items (Box 3, Folder 41)
      - Statements, notes, receipts, 1905-1912; 48 items (Box 3, Folder 42)
      - Statements, notes, receipts, 1913-1925; 46 items (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Account Books, 1882-1919; 37 items
      - Pierce Family and ranch expenses and earnings (includes records of ranch laborers);; 1 volume, 26 notes, 3 clippings, 3 receipts, 1897-1911; 33 items (Box 3, Folder 44)
      - Putah Creek Water Company, 1 volume, 1882-1885; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 45)
      - Checkbook with register, 1 volume, 1906; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 46)
      - Time book for Pierce Ranch laborers, 1 volume and 1 clipping, 1913-1919; 2 items (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Diaries, Notes, and Meeting Minutes, 1866-1930; Subseries 3.4.; 136 items
    The fourth subseries belonging to Series III is Diaries, Notes, and Meeting Minutes. It is arranged in chronological order. 45 of the 136 items in this subseries are diaries. Other items in this subseries are loose leaves of paper featuring notes or diary entries, meeting minutes, a bookmark, business cards, clippings, envelopes, a pencil, a sticker, an ink blotter, a map, and annotated travel guides. Like his father before him, George W. Pierce, Jr. made brief entries almost daily in his diaries. Most of Pierce's diaries deal with life on the Pierce Ranch and vicinity, and many include ranch accounts. The 1866 diary was written during Pierce's time as a high school student in Woodland, CA. Diaries written during 1871-1881 allow the researcher a glimpse into the life of Pierce as a young man helping his father on the ranch, going on hunting trips and excursions to Lake Tahoe, and studying at the University of California at Berkeley, CA. Pierce's 1910 diary includes a description of a trip he took across the United States and on to Panama. Pierce's 1921, 1893, and 1903 diaries also record trips he took across the United States. His 1923-1924 diaries describe his world travels as do his 1928-1929 diaries. Notes in this subseries were taken by Pierce during readings, lectures, and tours. Pierce also took notes on the number of trains passing through Davis in 1906 in order bolster his case to the State Farm Commission that Davis was an appropriate site for the proposed University Farm. Meeting minutes are from meetings of the Putah Creek Water Company and the Silica Brick Company.
    - Diary, 1866; 1 volume; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Diary and accounts, 1871; 1 volume (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Diary and accounts, 1872; 1 volume; 1 item bookmark (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Diary and accounts, 1873; 1 volume (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Diary, accounts, and lecture notes, 1874-1881; 1 volume (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Notes; University of California, Berkeley, CA, 1875; 1 volume (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Notes, written on 3 business cards for Gundlach, J. and Company, Sept. 9, 1878; 3 items (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Notes, copied from "Popular Science Monthly," article, "Can sound be produced by radiant energy?" June/July, 1881; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Notes on human speech and religion and notes on Independent Order of Odd Fellows celebration picnic, circa 1882; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Meeting Minutes; Putah Creek Water Company, Davisville, CA, 1882-1883; 1 volume (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Diary, 1889; 1 volume; 2 clippings; 2 envelopes (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - Diary, 1890; 1 volume (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - Diary, 1891; 1 volume (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Diary, 1892; 1 volume (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Diary, 1893; 1 volume (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Diary, 1894; 1 volume; 1 clipping (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Diary, 1895; 1 volume (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Diary, 1896; 1 volume (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Diary, 1897; 1 volume (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Diary and accounts, 1898; 1 volume (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Diary and accounts, 1899; 1 volume (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Diary and accounts, 1900; 1 volume (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Diary and accounts, 1901; 1 volume; 1 leaf (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Diary and accounts, 1902; 1 volume (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Diary and accounts, 1903; 1 volume (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Diary, 1904; 1 volume (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Diary, 1905; 1 volume (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Diary and accounts, 1906; 1 volume (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Notes on number of people in trains passing through Davis, CA (University Farm data), 1906; 1 leaf (Box 4, Folder 17)